Finding Aid for William W. Blume Papers, 1811-1825, [183-], and 1931-1963
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
William W. Blume papers 1811-1825 1830s 1931-1963
Blume, William Wirt, 1893-
85821 Aa 2
Professor of law at the University of Michigan; papers contain correspondence, teaching materials, papers relating to student discipline, proceedings of the University Judicial Council, 1950-1953; also research files and collected material relating to his study of Michigan's territorial court system; and copies of court records for Brown County, 1830s; also Wayne County Probate Court records, 1811-1825.
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
18 linear feet
Donor number 4471.
The collection is open to research.
William Wirt Blume began his legal career before actually completing his formal legal studies at the University of Michigan. Before enrolling in law school in 1926, Blume taught law at Soochow University in China. In 1931, he was appointed assistant professor of law at the University of Michigan. During his tenure at Michigan, Blume authored the six-volume work titled "Transactions of the Supreme Court of the Territory of Michigan, 1805-1836." Professor Blume retired from his distinguished legal career in 1963.
The William Wirt Blume papers include a memoir of his 192-1921 trip to China, a chronological correspondence file, teaching materials and other files related to his career at the University of Michigan, several reports on legal issues and research notes and files for his history of Michigan Territorial Supreme Court. The papers are arrange in five series: Travel, Correspondence, University of Michigan, Reports, and Notes and Research Material on Territorial Courts.
The series Notes and Research Material on Territorial Courts (boxes 6-18) contains Blume's notes and collected research materials relating to his study of U.S. territorial law and territorial court systems. Much of the emphasis of Blume's study concerned the Michigan Territorial Supreme Court and the various county and circuit courts under it. The researcher is directed to the Michigan Supreme Court record group for the original documents that Blume and his staff studied. This record group was transferred to the State Archives of Michigan in 2011. The researcher should also note that Blume's Transactions of the Supreme Court of the Territory of Michigan, with its extensive notes and historical commentaries is a superb introduction to Blume's career interests.
Subjects:
China--History--Republic, 1912-1949.; Court records.; Courts--Michigan.; Japan.; Michigan. Supreme Court.; University of Michigan--Faculty.; University of Michigan--Law School.; University of Michigan--Regulations.; University of Michigan--Students--Discipline.
Contributors:
University of Michigan. Judicial Council.; Michigan. Probate Court (Wayne County)
- Travel
  - Memoir of Travels in Japan and China 1920-1921 (Box 1)
- Correspondence
  - 1931-1963, 34 folders (Box 1)
- University of Michigan
  - Teaching Materials
    - American Civil Procedure, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - American Legal History 1955 (Box 2)
    - Constitutional Law (Box 2)
    - East Asiatic Area Law (Box 2)
    - Evidence, 2 folders (Box 2)
    - Evidence, Procedure and Jurisdiction (Box 3)
    - Federal Trial Practice and Procedure (Box 3)
    - Forms of Action (Box 3)
    - Introduction to the Legal System (Box 3)
    - Procedure (Box 3)
    - Restitution (Box 3)
    - Seminar on American History 1941-1942 (Box 3)
  - Trial and Appellate Practices (Box 4)
  - Faculty Instruction Records, ca. 1930-1950 (Box 4)
  - Grade Reports 1946-1951 (Box 4)
  - Student Papers 1940, 1962 (Box 4)
  - University Disciplinary Policies, 2 folders (Box 5)
  - University Judicial Council
    - Proceedings 1950-1953, 7 folders (Box 5)
  - Papers, relating to prize competition at University 1954, 1956 (Box 5)
  - Papers relating to Committee on University Lectures (Box 5)
  - Proposed statute on judicial jurisdiction 1951 (Box 5)
- Reports
  - Report of Special Committee on the Improvement of the Administration of Justice, 1941 (Box 5)
  - Report October 1928 of the Michigan Procedure Commission (Box 5)
  - Tentative rule revisions 1944 of the Michigan Supreme Court (Box 5)
  - Addresses 1928, 1934 to various bar associations (Box 5)
  - Pleading and procedure form book, 2 volumes (Box 5)
  - Miscellanea (Box 5)
- Notes and Research Material on Territorial Courts
  The series Notes and Research Material on Territorial Courts (boxes 6-18) contains Blume's notes and collected research materials relating to his study of U.S. territorial law and territorial court systems. Much of the emphasis of Blume's study concerned the Michigan Territorial Supreme Court and the various county and circuit courts under it. The researcher is directed to the Michigan Supreme Court record group for the original documents that Blume and his staff studied. The researcher should also note that Blume's Transactions of the Supreme Court of the Territory of Michigan, with its extensive notes and historical commentaries is a superb introduction to Blume's career interests.
  - Copies and Summaries of Pleadings, 1 volumes
    - County Court, Wayne County 1815-1829 (Box 6)
    - District Court, Huron and Detroit 1805-1810 (Box 6)
    - Court of Common Pleas, Wayne County 1796-1805 (Box 6)
  - Calendar of Cases, 1 volumes
    - Court of Quarter Sessions, Wayne County 1797-1804 (Box 6)
    - Court of Common Pleas, Wayne County 1796-1805 (Box 6)
  - Index to Papers, Court of Common Pleas, Wayne County 1796-1805 (Box 6)
  - Calendar of Cases, District Courts, Michigan Territory 1805-1810, 1 volumes
    - District of Huron and Detroit (Box 7)
    - District of Erie (Box 7)
  - Index of Criminal Cases (and civil cases for statutory penalties) in District Court for Huron, and Detroit and Erie; Supreme Court; and County Court, Wayne County (Box 7)
  - County Court, Wayne County, 1 volumes
    - Table of Cases (Box 7)
  - Notebook containing:
    - County Court (Wayne) Journal 1820-1821 (Box 7)
      [photocopies taken from microfilm]
    - Newspaper clippings re: Wayne County court records (Box 7)
    - Newspaper clippings re: laws in force in Indiana Territory 1800-1803 (Box 7)
    - Catalogue of books of William Woodbridge 1806 (Box 7)
    - Sibley's Notebook 1797-1799 (Box 7)
    - Miscellaneous Papers to 1810 (Box 7)
      (found with files of Supreme Court)
    - Miscellaneous Papers (Box 7)
      (found with files of Wayne County Court)
  - Index to Supreme Court Cases and Cases in Chancery (Box 8)
  - Calendar of Court Files and Miscellaneous Papers, Monroe County 1818-1848 (Box 8)
  - Michigan Unreported Opinions
    - 1805-1824 (Box 8)
    - 1825-1836 (Box 8)
    - 1805-1824 (Index-Digest) (Box 8)
  - Equity Cases taken from Blume's Transactions (Box 8)
  - Court of the Additional Judge
    - Journal 1823-1824 [photocopy] (Box 9)
    - Michilimackinac County
      - Journal and other records 1825, 1831-1833 [photocopies] (Box 9)
      - Journal 1831, 1833-1835 [typescript] (Box 9)
      - Judgment Records 1823-1836 [typescript) (Box 9)
        (2 versions)
      - Judgment Records: Chancery 1825 Criminal, 1831, 1833-1835 (Box 9)
        [typescript]
      - Analytical Table of Cases (Box 9)
    - Brown County
      - Judgment Records 1825-1835 [typescript] (Box 9)
      - Judgment Records: Criminal 1824-1834 (Box 9)
        (typescript])
      - Judgment Records: Civil 1825-1835 (Box 9)
        (typescript)
      - Calendar 1820s-1830s (Box 9)
        (photocopies)
      - Calendar 1820s-1830s (Box 10)
      - Calendar 1820s-1830s (Box 11)
      - Calendar 1820s-1830s (Box 12)
    - Crawford/Iowa County
      - Journal 1834-1836 (Box 12)
      - Judgment Record (Box 12)
      - Name Index to Calendars (Box 12)
    - Opinions of James Duane Doty (Box 12)
    - Card index to Doty's opinions (Box 12)
  - Journal (partial), of U.S. District Court for Kentucky District 1789 (Box 13)
  - Miscellaneous photocopies of clippings, correspondence, and legal materials (Box 13)
    (largely copies from holdings of Burton Historical Collection, Woodbridge and Sibley papers)
  - Notes on papers, in other collections (Box 14)
    (mainly Solomon Sibley papers, Burton Historical Collection)
  - Indiana Territorial Court Order Book (Box 14)
    (microfilm: positive and negative; and notes on order book)
  - Report and Explanatory Notes of the Revisors of the Statutes, Accompanying the Bill to Revise the General Laws of Wisconsin (Box 14)
    (microfilm: positive and negative)
  - Miscellaneous Notes, Correspondence, and Research Materials re: Territorial Court Studies (Box 15)
  - "American Legal History: Territorial Period" (Box 15)
  - Wayne County Probate Court Records 1811-1825 (Box 16)
    (includes some notes)
  - Wayne County Probate Court Records 1811-1825 (Box 17)
    continued
  - Wayne County Probate Court Records 1811-1825 (Box 18)
Articles by Blume
(Materials cataloged separately as DA 2 B658 A791)
Actions Quasi in Em Under Section 1665, Title 28, U.S.C. (Michigan Law Review, November 1951)
The "Common Questions" Principle in the Code Provision For Representative Suits. (Michigan Law Review, April 1932)
Jurisdictional Amount in Representative Suits. (Minnesota Law Review, April 1931)
Jury Selection Analyzed: Proposed Revision of Federal System. (Michigan Law Review, 1944)
Limitations and the Federal Courts. (Michigan Law Review, May, 1951)
Origin and Development of the Directed Verdict. (Michigan Law Review, March, 1950)
Place of Trial of Civil Cases. (Michigan Law Review, November, 1949)
The Place of Trial of Criminal Cases: Constitutional Vicinage and Venue. (Michigan Law Review, 1944)
Problem of Preserving excluded Evidence in the Appellate Record. (Minnesota Law Review, February, 1929)
A Rational Theory for Joinder of Causes of Action and Defenses and for the Use of Counterclaims. (Michigan Law Review, November, 1927)
Required Joinder of Claims. (Michigan Law Review, May, 1947)
The Scope of a Civil Action. (Michigan Law Review, October, 1943)
Theory of Pleading; A Survey Including the Federal Rules. (Michigan Law Review, January 1949)